Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is Kaf
Chet כ"ח. Kaf Chet. We begin a new perek פרק, perek, Chazkat
HaBatim חזקת הבתים, Chazkat HaBatim, third perek פרק perek of Bava Batra
בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. It is a very long perek פרק, perek,
it's over thirty daf דף, daf, although if you flip ahead you
will see that the actual size of the amount of words on
each page, well Gemara גמרא Gemara words is relatively small, because starting
with tomorrow's daf דף daf at least we're going to switch from
Rashi's רש"י Rashi's commentary to the Rashbam's רשב"ם Rashbam's and Rashbam רשב"ם
Rashbam was much wordier. The basic focus of this perek פרק perek
is about chazakah חזקה. chazakah. Chazakah חזקה chazakah is a word that
means a lot of different things in a lot of different contexts,
but here it basically means that if somebody is present on land
for three years, then now it is not that that entitles them,
gives them ownership of the land. It's not like some squatter's right,
but it serves as evidence that they are the owners of the
land, and if they make a legitimate claim, they say they purchased
it or something of that nature. They can't just say, oh well,
nobody ever complained so it's mine. But as we're going to see,
an important principle the Gemara's גמרא Gemara's going to introduce right at
the beginning is kol chazakah she'eini imah ta'anah einah chazakah כל חזקה
שאינה עמה טענה אינה חזקה. kol chazakah she'eini imah ta'anah einah chazakah.
If you just have been on the land for three years and
you're not giving any reason to say why it's legally yours, then
the chazakah חזקה chazakah is meaningless. But if you have a claim,
I bought it or something of that nature, then even if you
can't bring any other evidence, the fact that you've been on it
for three years and nobody has challenged your presence and your use
of it, that gives you a presumption of ownership, that serves as
evidence of ownership. Okay, of course part of a question you want
to ask is, well, where were the original owners? If the original
owners were like in China and they had no idea that you
were there and how could they have registered a complaint or so
on? And what were you doing that maybe was sufficient provocation for
them to have to respond and issue a complaint? So all of
those are things that we are going to discuss, but that is
the basic principle. That being there for three years, taking, making use
of it, serves
and the owners' lack of response serves as evidence that you are
the legitimate owner. But it has to be backed by a claim,
or maybe said better, that serves as backing to a claim of
legitimate ownership. So let's, and that's really going to be the major
focus for this entire perek פרק. perek. Let's take a look at
the opening mishna משנה, mishna, Kaf Chet Amud Aleph כ"ח עמוד א'.
Kaf Chet Amud Aleph. So, chazkat habatim vehaborot vehashichin vehame'arot חזקת הבתים
והבורות והשיחין והמערות, chazkat habatim vehaborot vehashichin vehame'arot, so the chazakah חזקה
chazakah for houses or for cisterns and canals and other types of
caves, basically other types of things that hold water, vehashovachot
והשובכות vehashovachot or pigeon cotes, dove cotes, vehamerchatzaot והמרחצאות vehamerchatzaot and bathhouses,
uveit habadin ובית הבדין uveit habadin and olive presses, uveit hashlachin ובית
השלחין uveit hashlachin and irrigated fields, ve'avadim ועבדים ve'avadim and slaves, and
all of these things are land, I mean except for the slaves
which are not themselves land but halachically are treated as land. So
far that's another important thing, that this idea relates to real estate,
land property, as well as slaves. Vechol shehu oseh peirot tadir וכל
שהוא עושה פירות תדיר, vechol shehu oseh peirot tadir, anything that regularly
produces fruit, that is something that you would have regular benefit from,
so chazkatan shalosh shanim miyom leyom חזקתן שלש שנים מיום ליום, chazkatan
shalosh shanim miyom leyom, if three years from day to day. So
the first point of the mishna משנה, mishna, as you can tell
by the list of all these different types of property, is not
to as with most times when we start a new topic, where
the Gemara גמרא Gemara normally, or the Rebbi רבי Rebbi in the
mishna משנה, mishna, normally does not do the job of first saying
let me tell you the basic principle that's operative here and let's
lay down the foundation and then let's talk about some more general
application and then more exceptions. No, usually it starts with some presumption
that you know the basic assumptions and it goes into a more
interesting case, okay? So here it's not that far afield, it doesn't
go to some very bizarre case, but it does start by categorizing,
not by telling you what the basic rule is, but by categorizing
different types of property. And by telling you that how long of
a duration is chazakah חזקה? chazakah? We speak about three years. Okay,
but that only applies to something that is something that you use
on a regular ongoing basis. A home is the best example. You
live in a home on a daily basis. It doesn't mean you're
in there every single day, and that also raises interesting points. Like
if I say I was a chazakah חזקה, chazakah, I was in
this apartment for three years, well what if you were on a
one-month
vacation in France? Does that count to interrupt your chazakah חזקה? chazakah?
So that's something we can worry about, okay? But the basic point
is three years is measured from I started here on January 1st
and three years later December 31st nobody ever said anything. So it
has to be continuous because the benefit you get from an apartment
and from a house is continuous, it's not seasonal. And that's really
true about all of these. Wells are used regularly, pigeon cotes are
type of a business, bathhouses, presumably even mara
מרא mara I think is... oh so the irrigated field.
Oh so
the irrigated field, the assumption here is that because it's by irrigation,
it's something that is not as seasonal, not as... not necessarily mean
that you harvest it on an ongoing basis, but it's sort of
something as opposed to fields, like in the winter the whole field
lays fallow there, it's seasonal. So for example if you look at
רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, right? רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, where's רש"י Rashi *Rashi*?
Yeah. בית השלחין מתוך שהמעיין בתוכה שמשקין אותה ממנו תדיר עושה פירות
תדיר *Beis Hashalchin mitoch shehama'ayan betocho shemashkin oso mimenu tadir oseh peiros
tadir*. So actually רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that actually it does produce
on a regular basis because actually one of the things and there's
a big תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* tries to figure this out that it
might not actually be enough that you're working it because if all
you're doing on the field is not benefiting from it, if all
you're doing on the field is you are irrigating it and plowing
and planting it, then I can say I wasn't going to say
anything. Guy wants to come into my field and start irrigating, be
my guest. So the question is, okay, but let's say it's a
cycle that ends with you harvesting it. So that case, the fact
that you were irrigating it and whatever plowing it beforehand counts towards
the חזקה chazaka *Chazakah* because it ends with you showing mastery that
you're going to take it. If all you did was to irrigate
it and then you walked away, you can't say, oh look, here's
my חזקה chazaka *Chazakah*, I irrigated it. Okay? But the assumption anyway
here is that this type of a thing is something that produces
on a more ongoing basis and therefore that actually creates a higher
demand. That means that you have to show in a sense that
you were using it for three years means you got the full
benefit out of it for those three years.
Okay, so the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* on א'
*Aleph* part, that's a חזקה Chazaka? *Chazakah* to take possession that is
not so- that is a good point, but that's the exact opposite
or close to the opposite. Meaning when we talk about like I
said, חזקה chazaka *Chazakah* is a word that means many different things
in different contexts. חזקה chazaka *Chazakah* if we're actually doing the act
of taking possession, I'm buying this land from you and I have
to do some act that shows mastery, actually there, it's actually the
opposite. It's I do something to improve the land is the basic
act of what a חזקה chazaka *Chazakah* is. Okay, but that is-
which you could ask why is that? Why can't חזקה chazaka *Chazakah*
be also taking benefit from the land? But here anyway, it's not
about an act of קניין *Kinyan* that takes possession, it's an act
that shows if I was not here legitimately, the owner should have
said something. So the basic point of these first things is something
that regularly produces. So for three years of something that you're getting
ongoing benefit means that you're there for an ongoing way for three
years. Okay, now
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is a little interesting because תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* also
talks about right presumably there still could be some seasonal aspect to
it. If you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, חזקת הבתים והבדים *Chazkas
Habattim vehaBaddim*, so one of the things is these olive presses. So
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says פירוש ריב"ם *Peirush Ribam* דתנן detnan פרק perek,
חומר בקודש עברו הגתות והבדים דמשמע שיש להם זמן קבוע *dehatnan perek
chomer bakodesh avru hagittot vehaBaddim demashma sheyesh lahem zman kavua*. So it
says when the time of the wine and the olive press is
over. So it sounds like those are seasonal and here it says
the press- an olive press is ongoing. היינו שרוב עולם דורכין אז
בזמן לקיטה *Haynu sherov olam dorchin az bizman lekita*. That's because most
people do the pressing at the time when the stuff is gathered.
אבל יש בני אדם שמטנין כל השנה ודורכין במעט מעט *Aval yesh
bnei adam shematnin kol hashana vedorchin bime'at me'at*. There are people that
use it slowly slowly over time. Now it's exactly not clear what
that means. Well, does that mean that if you're doing it as
a private enterprise and most people do it only one time in
the year, then maybe it doesn't fall into this משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah*?
But if you're doing it as a business, right? Then that might
mean that there's a high season and there's a low season, but
there's still the low season when you're still open for business, you
just get less business during that time. But obviously all these things
raise these types of questions, right? How do you measure all of
this stuff precisely? Anyway, let's take a look. So that's the first
point of the משנה mishnah, *Mishnah*. But if it's a שדה הבעל
*Sedeh HaBa'al*, if it is a field that survives by rain, okay,
חזקתה שלש שנים ואינה מיום ליום miyom leyom. *Chazkatah shalosh shanim ve'einah
mi-yom le-yom*. It's three years but it's not ongoing because there are
specific seasons. So you can get three seasons out of a field
without being there for a three full calendar years. Now how do
you measure those three seasons? So רבי ישמעאל אומר Rabbi Ishmael omer:
ג' חדשים בראשונה וג' באחרונה וי"ב חודש chodesh, באמצע *Rabbi Ishmael omer
gimmel chodashim barishona vegimmel ba'achrona veshneim asar chodesh ba'emtza*. Three at the
beginning, the entire 12 middle months and three at the end. So
right, it's a year and a half. So what are the three
at the beginning? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it is the three
months prior to the beginning of the year. So if you look
at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
where's רש"י Rashi *Rashi*?
It just says the last three months. Yes. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
has a whole question what does that mean, the three months before
ניסן *Nissan* or the three months also before תשרי *Tishrei*? Okay, I
think as רש"י *Rashi* clear but- hold on...
No, he doesn't say.
Oh, he says לפני ראש השנה *lifnei Rosh Hashanah*.
Yeah, לפני ראש השנה *lifnei Rosh Hashanah*, right, right. So okay, so
the planting season starts at ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, right? That's why
by the way one of the reasons תשרי *Tishrei* is considered the
beginning of the year, even though ניסן *Nissan* is the beginning of
the month. It's because from an agricultural perspective, it's also why school's
year starts in September, right? Because we used to be a more
agriculture-based society, and from an agricultural perspective, the planting season starts in
the beginning of the fall. Okay, so you plant, you plow, the
land is soft, you know, is soft or whatever, and then actually
the seeds stay protected over the winter, and then come the spring
and then they sprout forth and then you harvest and then the
summer you dry it out and so on, and that's basically the
planting season.
So, so, רש"י *Rashi* says that, you know, you might get in
a quick type of a crop, some crop that ripens very quickly,
you get it in in the summer, and then you have, that's
one year, and then you get the 12 months in the middle
and then you get some three months some fast type of a
crop at the end. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* has a whole discussion,
one of these big תוספות Tosafot *Tosfoses* is do you have to
actually harvest the crop or can you actually do some planting without
the harvest? That's the question about somebody could say I'm not going
to complain if you're just going to be planting. So if you
look at רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says the last three months, at
the end of this רש"י *Rashi*, right before רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*,
now where exactly tell you it is, it's about 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, about 12 lines
before the lines get wide, like right in the middle of the
narrow lines of רש"י *Rashi*, line starts with the word חדשים *Chadashim*.
He says ויש לו עדים שזרע בו ג' חדשים וכן בג' חדשים
ראשונים של אחרונה הרי זו חזקת שלוש שנים רצופות שאין לך אדם
הרואה את חברו שזורע את שדהו לכל פרוי העשויה לשנה ושותק *V'yeish
lo eidim she'zara bo gimmel chadashim v'chein b'gimmel chadashim rishonim shel achrona
harei zu chazkat shalosh shanim retzufot she'ein lecha adam haro'eh et chaveiro
she'zoreia et sadeihu l'chol piroy ha'asuyah l'shana v'shoteik*. So רש"י *Rashi* says
the last three months actually is you just did the planting in
the last three months and the last three תשרי חשון כסלו *Tishrei
Cheshvan Kislev*, but that's a חזקה chazakah. *chazakah* because the way you're
זורע *zoreia* in the land basically makes it clear that you're intending
to also harvest it. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* sort of takes
objection because תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says, you know, if you're just, if
you have not actually harvested it in the end, somebody could say
I'm not going to complain about a planting that didn't end with
a harvest. You planted and you walk out, I'm not going to
complain yet, right? So I'm just going to step in and I'll
take the harvesting that you did for me.
Yeah, what about the year in between?
I understand. What do you mean the year... okay, but I have
to not object for three years. I have three years of provocation
and the last year wasn't provocation. Now what רש"י *Rashi* could say
back is if the last year followed two years of planting and
harvesting, then that gives the context for the third year and you
should have. So I'm just pointing out that one of the questions
going on here is that תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* raises is, right, what
does presence mean? What are you doing in the field? And it
has to be some type of harvesting, which רש"י *Rashi* is sensitive
to, but he says well, it's clear enough from the end. Okay,
yes.
I'm just confused about the year in between. Do we talk about
that, like
why it needs to be a full 12-month calendar year?
You set it up as this is a type of field where
you're not doing something during part of the year, so what is
it?
Right, but you're sort of, well, you don't have to be working
during those, like, winter months,
but well, okay,
you mean why is the three months enough at the end and
three months at the beginning and you can't have three months in
the middle?
Right, so the point is, is why is a full 12-year, 12-month
period in the middle? Right, the 12-month period is a full year,
so that implies that you didn't do anything on the field in
that year, right?
And so, meaning what you did in that middle 12 months is
you planted for three months, you let the, sort of, it stayed
underground for three months of the winter, then you harvested for three
months in the spring, and then for the three months you left,
that's the way a normal agricultural year works, okay? Right, a normal.
Now the question is, the question you're asking is, if you can
make do, look, you all get, let's assume generally, let's assume for
a moment, right, that we're not, we didn't introduce the idea of
three months at the beginning and three months at the end. You
understand that I would say that a normal type of a field,
right, being on it a year means you do what the normal
cycle is. You plant for three months, okay, for the winter you're
not doing anything, there's nothing to do, right, but then you have
to be there next during the spring and you have to be
harvesting, and maybe you even have to be there in the summer
and let the stuff dry out in the field, which is what
they did in the fields, and you have to show that you're
using it the way it's normally used over the course of a
normal cycle of a year. That makes sense, right? So the only
question then becomes like, okay, but then why don't I have to
do that for three years, right? Why is this enough? And it's
true that the, you know, the sense here
is, I don't know how to explain this exactly, because it's like
seasonal, there's a way of explaining that it doesn't really explain the
last three months, but there's a way of explaining that the first
three months, if I did some type of a thing that had
a very short season, then I actually used that thing for, like,
for a, you know, I did one of, you know, let's read
the end of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, maybe it'll get a little
clearer, maybe not, maybe I'm not so clear in my own head
about it, but let's read the end, let's start to read the
end, hold on to your questions, I want to read the end
of the משנה *Mishnah* because it might... maybe not, maybe I'm not
so clear in my own head about this, but let's read let's
try to read the end. Hold on to your questions. I want
to read the end of the משנה because it might or may
not clarify it, but anyway it'll give us more data, so I'll
come back to you, I promise. Let's read the end of the
משנה, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי ישמעאל אומר
ג' חודשים בראשונה וג' באחרונה וי"ב באמצע הרי י"ח חודש. Rabbi Ishmael
omer gimel chodashim barishona vegimel ba'achrona veyud bet ba'emtza harei yud chet
chodesh. רבי עקיבא אומר חודש בראשונה וחודש באחרונה וי"ב באמצע הרי י"ד
חודש. Rabbi Akiva omer chodesh barishona vechodesh ba'achrona veyud bet ba'emtza harei
yud daled chodesh.
Now אמר רבי ישמעאל. amar Rabbi Ishmael. Now Rabbi Ishmael now clarifies
the 18 months. Rabbi Akiva even had 14 months. במה דברים אמורים
בשדה לבן. bamei devarim amurim bisdeh lavan. When is that true? That's
about a wheat field, okay? It's white because you look at it,
it's all white when it's growing. אבל בשדה אילן, aval bisdeh ilan,
if it's a tree, if it's an orchard, if there are trees,
or which also includes not just trees but also vines and so
on, so כנס את תבואתו kanas et tevuato ומסיק את
זיתיו. umasik et zeitav. תבואתו tevuato grain here, the רש"י and תוספות
Tosafot, based on the גמרא Gemara says this actually means your grapes.
So you gather in your grapes,
you gather in your olives, מסיק masik is just the verb used
for olives, you gather in your olives, כנס את קיצו, kanas et
kaitzo, you gather in your figs that are drying out on the
in the field, הרי אלו ג' שנים, harei elu shalosh shanim, that
counts for three years because you basically did three types of harvesting
of three different plants and that counts as three years.
Is this all one field?
This is all, well, it's an orchard that has different types of,
yeah, things growing from it. Okay. But you're right, why don't you
say, 'Well, this is a חזקה chazakah of this section and this
is a חזקה chazakah. for this section?' So it's clear, so what's
clear here by the end, right, is that you don't need even
three calendar years. All of this could take place within one year,
right? But it's some idea of like three types of harvests, that
becomes clear at the end. So how to deal with this idea
in the middle, which your question I think essentially is, is that
if all you really do need is three harvests, why do you
need the 12 months in the middle? Why do you need to
do three months and get some quick type of a thing there,
and then three months and three months, assuming that that works in
terms of the seasons, right? So I don't really know. I would
say that the sense is that there are, you know, that there
are like three concepts that are going on here. Which is one
is the straight three calendar years, מיום ליום. miyom leyom, The other
is something that sort of represents three years. So for example, you
know sometimes there's an idea which is like יום אחד בחודש yom
echad bachodesh counts as a חודש, חודש אחד בשנה chodesh echad bashana
counts as a שנה. shana. So the stuff in the middle sounds
like what we're talking about is it doesn't have to literally be
three years מיום ליום, it has to be it has to sort
of represent three years. So obviously you need the anchor in the
middle, but then a little bit at the beginning and a little
bit at the end. The beginning counts to represent a year, the
end counts to represent a year, and the middle is a full
year. But we're not directly looking at, you know, harvests. We're looking
at something that is a virtual three years as opposed to a
literal three years. And then by the end we're looking at a
case of three harvests. Okay, so that's sort of what we're dealing
with. Exactly how to explain, I mean I know it's bothering you,
which is like, 'I still don't get the logic of the middle
idea.' I get the logic of the beginning, it's three literal years.
I get the logic at the end, that it's three harvests. Okay,
but like what's exactly with the middle? Why does it count like
a month at the beginning and a month at the end and
why do you need the full 12 months in the middle? That's
basically what you were asking, or?
Yeah, I mean just like how are we measuring it, if we're
measuring it by doing one full thing that only takes three months
then great and if we're measuring it by a
year then.
Right, there's somehow some idea that you need three calendar years but
it can be like an approximate three years, a virtual three years.
So you need a year in the middle and the little at
the beginning and the little at the end.
But why so for the three different produce, that's like pretty weird
too. Right, but that's like a different idea altogether. That's like three
harvests. Right. The middle idea is like three years but not literal,
three years but approximate. And you somehow get it by the year
in the middle and the little at the beginning and the little
at the end. But why exactly that works for like an irrigated
field, how, what's the logic also of the correlation of those two
is also not exactly clear. David, you had a question?
Yeah, a question on the end first is how in the world
would you know that תבואתו tevuato means grapes?
Well, I used רש"י and תוספות and I assume the גמרא Gemara
is going to say it. I'd have to double check the גמרא.
Gemara. Otherwise you would definitely not know it. Okay. But also because
it said שדה אילן sde ilan and תבואה tevuah you don't have
in a שדה אילן, sde ilan, that's a שדה לבן. sde lavan.
Yeah, but you had a question before that David.
I guess the question was is so what we're saying is not
that the 12 months is a 12 month gap but the 12
months is additional months.
Oh, it's part of the 12 months. Oh yeah, that wasn't clear.
Yeah, the 12 months is a normal 12 month cycle of planting
and harvesting and grow-out. Okay, yeah.
But I'm still not understanding why you need a whole three years.
Who would let somebody be on their field and harvest their own
crops if it's theirs? Just one harvest should be enough for the
whole thing. In other words, you know, say okay he wasn't there
then okay he could, if he wasn't there then you get a
longer time.
Alright, so fine, so we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara. But
obviously the point is is that it's not enough that there was
provocation, it's how much lack of responding to provocation serves as real
evidence, you know, as serves enough to substitute for the presence of
real documentation.
Okay, so Someone taking my produce is okay maybe stealing?
Yeah I don't know whatever who knows?
But I can't imagine that someone has a field that's fallow and
then somebody else comes and starts working it, you know, not necessarily.
Okay
exactly.
And I'll get around to it I'll sue you whatever there are
witnesses.
Okay maybe five years whatever. So we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara.
All right. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan.
Anyway thankfully so yes it is complicated particularly this middle opinion about
what does it mean to have three virtual years and like and
why that and why that specifically as for דבעל Dabaal even if
דבעל Dabaal is more regular you know exactly how that works conceptually
we'll definitely have to return to that. But anyway thankfully the גמרא
Gemara starts us off at the most conceptual basis and says what
is this idea of חזקה? chazakah Where does it come from? Before
we get to worrying about these different types of fields. So let's
take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan שמעתי מהוכאי אושא
Shamati mehochei Usha I heard from those that went to אושא. Usha.
אושא Usha was where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was after it left יבנה.
Yavne. Okay. So and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is a very early
אמורא. Amora.
So הוכאי אושא Hochei Usha what they were the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin?
Yeah the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the people from the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, yeah.
So how do we refer to them?
Well I don't think he means the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, I think he
means from people who came from אושא Usha like he doesn't mean
I heard from the סנהדרין Sanhedrin directly. Okay. שמעתי מהוכאי אושא Shamati
mehochei Usha שהיו אומרים she-hayu omrim they used to say מנין לחזקה
ג' שנים mina lan le-chazaka gimel shanim how do you know the
idea that a חזקה chazakah is for three years?
משור המועד Mishor HaMuad from the from a שור המועד Shor HaMuad
from a habitual gorer. This is the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says the same
thing. מה שור המועד כיון שנגח ג' נגיחות נפיק ליה מחזקת תם
וקאי ליה בחזקת מועד. Ma shor ha-muad keivan she-nagach gimel negichot nafik
lei me-chezkas tam ve-kaimei lei be-chezkas muad. Three this is an idea
from חזקה chazakah which is three times establishes a pattern. Okay. So
if an ox gores for three times we no longer say that
it's goring is irregular we now say that it's a habitual gorer.
It no longer has a status of a תם Tam it has
a status of a מועד Muad of a habitual gorer. הכא נמי
Hacha nami so here too כיון דאכל תלת שנין נפיק ליה מרשות
מוכר וקיימא ליה ברשות לוקח keivan de-achal telat shanin nafik lei me-rashut
mocher ve-kaimei lei be-rashut lokeach once you're eating on a field for
three years
it leaves the possession of the of the seller of the original
owner and is established as in your possession. Now what the heck
does this mean? First of all if you understood חזקה chazakah as
only an idea of establishing a pattern of behavior so we could
say okay you've been on that field for three years we've now
established a pattern of behavior that you are a regular harvester and
user of the field maybe you're a regular גזלן gazlan right? So
even if you just think about the comparison the analogy without even
asking the logic it's not enough to say you are habitual that's
not just the idea of a pattern of behavior. What the point
here is also that it's a status issue. The label we attach
to this שור shor is תם. Tam. After three times we shift
its label its identity shifts. Okay. So you now have been acting
as the owner for three years okay after you've been acting as
the owner because that's what an owner does. I mean that's what
a sharecropper does if it's true. But anyway but you know a
sharecropper would then share his crop would pay you know you haven't
been sharing your crop you've been taking the whole thing. So you've
been acting as an owner for three years after that now your
status has changed. Now you switch from being a you know a
squatter to an owner. It's a status change. Now that's all very
nice but like why is that legal? Like the logic for the
שור המועד Shor HaMuad is because we want to know whether it's
going to likely gore or not gore. Why does this give you
rights which you're not entitled to? So but it seems like the
גמרא Gemara is giving us a pure formalism. It's almost like squatters'
rights right where we always go to the effort to tell people
when we learn חזקה chazakah it's not like just you're there you
have rights to it. It sounds like הוכאי אושא Hochei Usha actually
saying otherwise. They're basically saying you're there nobody complained that makes it
yours. You know you've exerted your dominance over it that gives it
to you. Okay. Now תוספות of course and רש"י and תוספות try
to make this into the more normal idea that no no no
what it means is nobody's objecting for three years you're showing that
they were okay blah blah blah but that's not what the way
the גמרא Gemara sounds and תוספות what?
and you're claiming that you acquired
and you're claiming that you acquired but at this stage that's not
what the גמרא Gemara sounds like and תוספות actually in one opinion
acknowledge that this seems to be just some formal rule that you're
entitled to it even if you didn't own buy it like legally.
If you look at the last line of תוספות עם שור המועד
Im shor ha-muad תוספות says
where is it?
No the last line of the עד נגיחה רביעית ad negicha revit
that תוספות two lines from the
bottom תוספות says ואומר רי דסלקא דעתך דהמקשה דהכי יליף מה התם
כי נגח ג' פעמים נפק ליה מחצי נזק לנזק שלם הכי נמי
כיון דאכלה שלוש שנים ולא מיחה נפק ליה מרשות מוכר לרשות לוקח
אע"ג דמסתבר בלא טעמא הוא. ve-omer Ri de-salka daitach de-hamakshat de-hachi yalif
mah hatam ki nagach gimel peamim nafak lei me-chatzi nezek le-nezek shalem
hachi nami keivan de-achlah shalosh shanim velo mikhah nafak lei me-rashut mocher
le-rashut lokeach af al gav de-mistaver belo tama hu. Okay. No reason.
Okay but that's just a thing. Your status changes, you change status,
you're no longer a squatter, you're now an owner. That's actually what
the גמרא Gemara sounds like. Of course the גמרא Gemara is going
to push back because that's not fair and that's not logical, but
that's at least the initial set. Yes.
What is it? Is it that you're the owner or that the
burden of proof switches?
Doesn't sound like that. I mean, you could say that, but no,
because then what would the person prove? How could you prove I
didn't sell it to you? It sounds like no, you're the owner.
That gives you rights. Okay, now let's read a little more. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: אימא, Ima, so that's our argument, it's
like a שור מועד. Shor Mu'ad. Obviously you understand the attraction of
that. Three and three, and three makes חזקה. chazakah Three establishes a
pattern, so that's obviously the attraction of making that comparison. אושה Usha
is אמוראים? Amoraim? That's already...
well, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is like a first generation of תנאים,
Tannaim, of אמוראים. Amoraim. I know, but אושה, Usha, I mean it's
also funny because אושה Usha was still early on. It was way,
way... yeah, I don't know, I don't know exactly what הולכי אושה
holchei Usha means.
Anyway, I'm not sure, the word is גולים מן אושה. golim min
Usha.
Yeah, but the סנהדרין Sanhedrin left אושה, Usha, the סנהדרין... Sanhedrin... by
רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's time the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was no longer, I
mean had been I think no longer in אושה Usha for more
than a generation by רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's time.
What, but they were in that area at least?
They were still in... I know, so I'm just saying but the
גלות galus to אושה Usha was many generations before רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. What, הולכי מאושה? holchei mi-Usha?
Oh, you mean הולכי מאושה, holchei mi-Usha, you mean from, so why's
he... why'd he say הולכי יבנה holchei Yavne
or whatever? I don't know. Anyway, I'm not sure. Let's move on.
Anyway, it says like this,
okay,
maybe it just means they're reporting, there was a מסורה mesorah going
back to אושה, Usha, that could make more sense too. You know,
that I heard from some tradition going back to אושה. Usha. Okay.
The רי"ף Rif says that, a tradition going back to אושה? Usha?
Okay, that makes sense. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אימא שור מועד עד נגיחה רביעית לא מיחייב הכא נמי עד
שנה רביעית לא קיימא ברשותיה. Ima Shor Mu'ad ad negichah revi'is lo
mechayev hacha nami ad shanah revi'is lo ka'ima bireshusei. One minute, a
שור מועד Shor Mu'ad doesn't pay full damages, it three times it
becomes a מועד, Mu'ad, but it doesn't pay until it gores the
fourth time. So here too, you know, maybe you have to live
in it the fourth year. Now of course that's a little crazy
question. Its status changes after three times, and the consequence occurs when
it gores the fourth time because now there's a new payment to
be made. So here too the consequence should begin at the beginning
of the fourth year, now it's mine. Anyway, let's see what the
גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is. הכי השתא, Hachi ashta, which is essentially the
גמרא'ס Gemara's answer. הכי השתא? Hachi ashta? What type of a comparison
is that? התם מכיוון דנגח שלוש נגיחות הוי מועד ואידך כי לא
נגח מאי משלם? Hatam mikivan de-nagach shalosh negichos havei mu'ad ve-idach ki
lo nagach mai meshalam? After three times, now it's a
מועד. mu'ad. And if it doesn't do anything, okay, you got a
מועד mu'ad ox that has nothing to pay because it didn't do
anything that there's a consequence to its
status. הכא כיון דאכל תלת שני קיימא ליה ברשותיה. Hacha keivan de-achal
telos shanim ka'ima lei bireshusei. Now the status changes, it's now yours.
So now the גמרא Gemara asks the question which shows that the
גמרא Gemara really thought that this did it all by itself. It
just made it yours because of your showing, demonstrating your ownership. Because
now the
גמרא Gemara says: אלא מעתה חזקה
שאינה עמה טענה תהוי חזקה. Ela me-ata chazakah she-eini imah ta'ana te-havei
chazakah. You shouldn't need to make a טענה ta'ana that you bought
it. You should just say, 'Why is it mine? I was here
three years. Nobody complained. That makes it mine.' Three years establishes me
as the owner. So then why is it true that if there's
no טענה, ta'ana, it's not good? אלמה תנן כל חזקה שאינה עמה
טענה אינה חזקה? Alamah tenan kol chazakah she-eini imah ta'ana eina chazakah?
Why do we teach in a משנה:
a חזקה chazakah. that does not have a טענה ta'ana to back
it up is not a חזקה. chazakah, It's not good. So clearly
חזקה chazakah, does not by itself change the status.
Wait, the טענה ta'ana here is the guy who's being מחזיק machzik
is claiming...
Yes, I am the owner, or is being...
no, that's called a מחאה.
mechah. טענה Ta'ana is: here's my claim why I'm a legitimate owner.
I bought it from you, you donated it to me. Yes, there
is a טענה ta'ana being made in court which the חזקה chazakah.
serves to back up. The חזקה chazakah by itself does not make
it mine. The חזקה chazakah? backs up a claim of legitimate ownership.
I'm sorry, every time I'm at a מחאה mechah I'm going to
claim that it's mine?
No, no. I show up after three years. Michael, what have you
been doing on my field? If you say, 'Well, you didn't say
anything to me and I've been here three years, it's mine,' that's
חזקה שאינה עמה טענה. chazakah she-eini imah ta'ana. If you say, 'What
do you mean what am I doing here? I bought it from
you three years ago. You gave it to me three years ago.
I won it in a poker game from you three years ago.'
That's a טענה. ta'ana.
That's only if he מערער, mahrer, but let's say if you're not
מערער... mahrer...
Well, if you're not מערער, mahrer, nobody's doing anything. I mean, what...
that's the ערעור, i'ur, what are you doing on my land?
Yes, right. But if nobody's complaining, then everybody's going along with their
lives. The need to produce a חזקה chazakah is that the ownership
is being challenged. Okay? And if the ownership is being challenged, then
him saying that I have a חזקה chazakah, does not make me
win.
But if it's ten years, then I can just say... You could...
no. You can be here a hundred years. If I prove that
I owned it first and you came after me, then either you
need a שטר shtar or you need a חזקה. chazakah Anything short
of a שטר shtar or a חזקה, chazakah the principle... maybe that's
a good point to say an important concept here. Now here's an
important point. make a very important concept that's going to dominate to
sort of play out for the whole rest of the פרק, perek
which is, as opposed to מטלטלין, metaltelin, by מטלטלין metaltelin the הלכה
halachah is חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו. chazakah mah
shetachas yad adam harei hu shelo. Ownership is—possession is a presumption of
ownership, like possession is nine-tenths of the law. So basically, I could
show that I was driving around in my nice Ferrari yesterday and
I've been talking about it for the last year about how I
love it, I would never sell it for a million dollars, and
Michael now is driving around with it with the keys, and I
say Michael, what did you do? You stole my car! I left
it parked in the parking lot with the keys and you took
it. He says, no, you sold it to me. And since he's
in possession of it, I have the burden of proof. Okay, that's
by מטלטלין. metaltelin. Doesn't matter how much it was known to be
mine and how much I've been proclaiming I would never sell it,
if you're in possession of it, you're presumed the owner, I have
the burden of proof.
So you still need a claim. He still needs a claim.
Okay, but I'm just saying ownership—possession is a presumption of ownership with
a claim, with a claim of legitimacy. קרקע karka is the opposite.
קרקע, karka, the principle is, because there's no sense of really having
it in your pocket and possessing it. So the sense is חזקת
מרא קמא, chezkat mara kamma, קמא. kamma. No, it's presumed to be
owned by the person who we know was the last legitimate owner.
I mean you could always say how does that start, but okay,
we can't figure that out, whatever. We live in society, we start
with presumptions. Whoever the presumption was of the last legitimate owner is
the presumption of the current owner. Like I was the last known
legitimate owner of this land. Michael's been on it for twenty years,
for fifty years, and I say Michael, what have you been doing
on my land for fifty years? If there were not a הלכה
halachah of this פרק of חזקה, chazakah, he could—he would not be
believed unless he could produce a שטר. shtar. In the absence of
documentation, the fact that I was known—now, or witnesses that saw me
sell it to him. But since I was known as the last
owner, I am presumed as still the current owner unless he can
produce direct testimony that I sold it to him or a שטר,
shtar, which is like sort of direct testimony, or חזקה. chazakah Okay,
and that's the way that חזקה chazakah basically with a טענה. ta'anah.
And all of those things are with a טענה. ta'anah. He says,
here's how I came in legitimate legal possession of it. But if
all he says is, I know it was yours but since you
didn't complain it became mine because I was on it, that's חזקה
שאין עמה טענה, chazakah she'ein imah ta'anah, and that's what they said,
if it was really based on שור המועד, shor hamu'ad, you would
say okay, you were on it, you get it. But no, it
really does not work that way. It has to back up legitimacy
plus, you're saying.
What do you mean plus? Meaning plus a טענה. ta'anah.
No, three years or ten years or fifty years.
Yeah, yeah, of course. It's three years and on. Of course, yes.
There's no higher limit. It doesn't
expire, correct. Yeah, but מטלטלין, metaltelin, you
said how could you prove that you didn't sell it to
me, so if I'm
driving your Ferrari, how could you rebut the presumption?
Yeah, it's a good point.
And you don't have—never reported stolen without witnesses.
Right, without witnesses of theft. Now there are a subcategory of מטלטלין
metaltelin which are things that are sort of like if I have
sheep, things that generally change hands, or דברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר, devarim
ha'asuyim lehash'il ulehashkir, things that you generally rent out. So there, your
possession is like—I mean sheep change hands in the sense that they
wander around or whatever. Okay. But things that are not in a
category of things you normally rent out and so on, then yeah,
you're in trouble. If you're going to give him your Ferrari, lend
him your Ferrari, you better have witnesses that you lent it to
him, and don't leave your keys in your car!
No, keeping the שטר shtar doesn't mean anything because there's no שטר
shtar by מטלטלין. metaltelin. I could hold on to the שטר, shtar,
I just sell it to you, you gave me—we met in the
parking lot, you gave me
a briefcase full of a hundred thousand dollars, you did a קנין
kinyan on it. You don't need—the whole idea of having a deed
to a—yeah,
but if you had a rental contract.
Oh, a rental contract! Yes, yes, yes, yes. Right, a rental contract
is different.
That's for—for example, because you have a שטר, shtar, you have the
vehicle registration.
But that would not—that's not meaningful according to הלכה. halachah. I mean,
now, the question of how much דינא דמלכותא dina demalchuta would change
those
assumptions, fine, as circumstantial evidence, right? That's true. Okay. But I was
trying to give a nice colorful example. Yes. I keep on dropping
these hints, I wonder one of these times my birthday will roll
around, people will pick up on the hints. Yes. Yes.
If you need a claim, what's the purpose of the חזקה? chazakah.
Because you then—you don't need to produce the שטר. shtar. You don't
need the physical documentation.
What do you mean—what's the claim then?
I—yes, I bought it from you. I don't have the שטר, shtar,
the document, but I've been on it three years, that proves it's
mine. The שטר, shtar, the
חזקה Chazaka. represents—replaces the need for testimony or
שטר. shtar. You do have to go to court. I mean, you
know.
Then when you're saying testimony, you mean a witness.
What?
Michael's going to have to produce witnesses that he was on it
for three years. You still need witnesses. Okay? Because then it's just
a he said, he said type of thing. Whatever. But he's not
going to have to produce witnesses that saw me sell it to
him. Okay.
Yeah, those were terrible examples you gave. Ferrari started 1948.
Sorry, okay, with you. 1947. Sorry, okay, with you, 1947. Okay, moving
on. All right, so now the גמרא. Gemara. All right, חברה. chevre.
חברה, chevre, exactly. ואידך, ve-idach, כי... ki...
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says if really being on it itself
created ownership and then you wouldn't need to have a claim that
you purchased it, אלמא תנן, al-ma tnan, why do we teach in
the משנה, כל חזקה שאין עמה טענה אינה חזקה? kol chazaka she-ein
imah ta-anah einah chazaka? טעמא מאי, tama mai,
so clearly it's not just being on it makes you the owner.
So then the גמרא Gemara says now the גמרא Gemara gets to
what the real reasons are and then whether שור, shor, whether the
ox still is relevant or not we'll see.
טעמא מאי דאמרינן דילמא כדקאמר השתא. tama mai de-amrinan dilma kedeka-amar hashta.
No, so here's the answer. Why is it that if a... that
we had if there's no טענה, ta-anah, you don't win it? Because
wait
a minute... Right, because I'm sorry, the reason is is because we
say that if you're on it for three years it's yours because
that's what you're claiming, you're claiming that it's yours. Maybe it is
like you said, you said it's yours.
אי לא טעין אנא ליטעני, ei lo tayin ana liteini, if you're
not going to make a claim that it's yours, why would we
make that claim for you? Now that's still interesting, right? The גמרא
Gemara still does not want to give up this idea of the
שור. shor. It's like the classic explanation of why you need a
טענה ta-anah is is because like property doesn't change hands without some
legitimate transaction, right? But then the idea of what we're learning from
the שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal seems less relevant because what does the
idea of the... I'm not שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, I meant שור
המועד. shor ha-muad. How does the שור המועד shor ha-muad all of
a sudden make it yours? So what it still the גמרא Gemara
sort of seems to be saying is, it really is the idea
that being there three years makes it yours, but you have to
frame the meaning of why are you there three years, right? You
could be three years as a sharecropper, you could be three there
because you're hired by the owner. So a three years that is
framed in the way that sort of says it's a three years
of ownership then that creates an... that establishes you as owners. When
it's not being framed that way it doesn't. So if you're not
framing it, if you're not, you know, sort of positioning yourself as
an owner, we're not going to position you as an owner. But
the גמרא Gemara is still not really using this as the normal
explanation which is the psychological point that if oh, if he's not
complaining and he's not objecting, it shows he must have sold it
to you. Because then the comparison to שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal is
irrelevant. It really still wants to use שור הנסקל... shor ha-niskal... I
keep on saying שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, שור המועד, shor ha-muad, right?
As somehow showing three times establishes identity, changes status. Oh, you need
a טענה, ta-anah, that's just to give a meaning to the presence,
but fundamentally it's not a substitute proof and an explanation, you know,
it's not evidence in a court, it's about change of status. But
the claim frames what the meaning of that presence is. Okay? That
seems to be the point of the גמרא. Gemara.
It might be silly that someone's got to name that שור shor
as מועד. muad.
Well, you need a process in
בית דין.
beis din. Yeah, so that's my point.
So we're going to get to that... Yeah, so we're going to
get to that a little bit right now. So מתקיף לה רב
אבירא, maskif lah Rav Avira, אלא מעתה, ela me-ata, if that's true,
מחאה שלא בפניו לא תהוי מחאה. mecha-ah she-lo be-fanav lo tehei mecha-ah.
If somebody objects to your being there not in the presence of
the owner, then that... not in your presence, Michael's on my land
and I'm away in France and I
objected, so that shouldn't be meaningful. And that shouldn't... because normally if
I object during the three years, it stops his possession. And even
we're going to learn, even an objection not in his presence. Now
that should not work. Why should that not work? דומיא דשור המועד,
dumya de-shor ha-muad, the same way that that's true by this
ox, מה שור המועד בפניו בעינן, mah shor ha-muad be-fanav bainan, when
you testify against a guy's goring ox, you have to do it
in the guy's presence, הכא נמי בפניו בעינן, hacha nami be-fanav bainan,
here too it should have to be in the guy's presence if
we really mean to be serious about this comparison. Now, of course,
well, let's read through the answer, but then point out that that's
an in... not a good analogy. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says התם
והועד בבעליו כתיב. hatam ve-hu-ad bi-valav ksiv. No, no, no. There, it's
a פסוק. pasuk. It says you warn the owners. The owners have
to be present. You're giving testimony against somebody, they need to be
present in court in order to, you know, defend themselves. הכא חברך
חברא אית ליה וחברא דחברך חברא אית ליה, hacha chavrach chavrah is
lei ve-chavrah de-chavrach chavrah is lei, your friend has a friend
and your friend's friend has a friend and the word gets around,
which is the general explanation the גמרא Gemara has that you can
object not in somebody's presence and eventually, right? Now we just friend
everybody by Facebook and that's, you know, and you have shared friends.
That's חברך חברא אית ליה, chavrach chavrah is lei, right?
Exactly.
That's how you can do it שלא בפניו. she-lo be-fanav. You know
Facebook recommends friends, you and this person have so many shared friends,
have so many friends in common. That's חברך חברא אית ליה. chavrach
chavrah is lei. Anyway, so that's how you also do a מחאה
שלא בפניו. mecha-ah she-lo be-fanav. But anyway, the גמרא's Gemara basic explanation
is you can do it in France and eventually the word will
get to the other person. Now, that's all very nice, but what
the heck is the comparison?
מחאה mecha-ah interferes with establishing the חזקה, right? So creating the מחאה
macha'ah is I warn the owner, I warn Jenna three times in
her presence and I say, "Your שור shor is goring, your שור
shor is goring," so doing it directly in front of Jenna is
a way of creating that status. Here the גמרא Gemara should say,
it shouldn't be asking that מחאה macha'ah out of the presence shouldn't
work, it should be asking that חזקה out of somebody's presence should
not work. If I want to change the status of this field
from your field to my field, then the same way I want
to change the status of your ox, I need to do it
in your presence. If I want to change the status of your
field, I need to be taking possession in your presence in order
to now change its status. So תוספות basically says that's what the
גמרא Gemara means.
I mean, I'm going to embrace תוספות, I don't know if it's
פשט, pshat, but it's the logical פשט. pshat. He says חזקה means
something because it's a taking of possession in the absence of objection.
So what creates the חזקה, the same way by the ox, what
creates the status is the warn... well, it's the goring followed by
the warning of the owner. What takes works for the חזקה is,
yeah, but with the three times, what works for the חזקה is
the taking of possession followed by, like the goring is followed by
the warning, the taking of possession followed by the silence, followed by
the non-reaction, the non-מחאה. macha'ah. That's part of what establishes my presence.
So therefore what the גמרא's Gemara saying is that non-מחאה macha'ah should
have to happen as it were essentially in the original owner's presence,
right? So if the owner's in France, if I'm in France and
Michael is doing it, it's not an אי מחאה בפניו, ee macha'ah
befanov, right? It's the provocation and my silence or whatever, it's not
happening, I'm not directly encountering it, so it should not be strong
enough to change the status of it, okay? So it's like if
Jenna's cow gored not in her presence or she was warned not
in her presence, it's not powerful enough to change the status. So
if Michael is taking possession not in my presence and I'm not
being confronted with it and being silent and that's not happening as
it were in the presence, the quasi-silence, then that should not be
strong enough to change the status. And the גמרא's Gemara answer is,
no, everything is in everybody's presence, word gets around even if you're
not there. Okay, now of course say that by the ox as
well. Okay, but the ox requires a formal process of testifying in
court, and you don't testify with somebody, you know, in their absence,
because that's the nature of that formal process. Exactly, that's a court
process. This is not a court process. What do you mean? Oh,
so for the מחאה macha'ah you need witnesses, true, but it's not
a court process.
Okay, so you can do it in front of... רש"י has a
different approach, but it's predicated on the idea that this is really
about the שטר shtar proof. Right, true. And רש"י says that the
claimant says, "If I had known that you were going to protest,
right, I would have held on to my שטר." shtar. So רש"י's
already trying to introduce the more logical explanation and the less formal
one that we're going to get to, that it's all about I
wasn't bothering with my שטר shtar because you weren't, but my point
is I'm trying to avoid that because I don't think it's פשט
pshat at this stage in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara really
seems to take seriously this idea: you do something three times, it
changes status, right? So there has to be a meaning to the
doing it three times. You have to frame it, you have to
say, "I'm the owner, you don't have a claim," and so on.
Okay, let's keep on going. Eventually we're going to get to what
I would consider the more logical explanation, but I want to treat
this גמרא Gemara like give it its due. So let's keep on
going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולרבי מאיר דאמר ריחק
נגיחותיו חייב קירב נגיחותיו לא כל שכן? U'le'Rabbi Meir d'amar richek negichosav
chayav kirev negichosav lo kol shekein? Now, the normal opinion is it
has to gore three times on three separate days, I mean, once
a day. But what if it gored three times on one day?
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it doesn't become a שור המועד,
shor hamu'ad, it's not habitual enough. It's like it's got something crazy,
you know, it had a bad day. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
said no, it's all the more dangerous! If it, if you say
when it's ריחק נגיחותיו, richek negichosav, if it's separated its gorings, it's
חייב, chayav, then קירב נגיחותיו, kirev negichosav, if it's goring three times
in one day, how much more so is this a dangerous, violent
ox. So if that's true, you should say the same here. If
you eat three times in a shorter period of time, all the
more so is it a, you know, if you want to say
provocation, but we're not even deal, you know, all the more so
does it establish you as the owner. You did something that demonstrated
your possessing of it in the face of the owner, and that
should be strong enough. So the גמרא Gemara says אכלה תלתא פירי
בחד יומא. achla telasa pirei bechad yoma. Let's say you ate from,
you know, three fruit on the same day. To go, and maybe
תאנה, te'ena, like a תאנה. te'ena. Now, the reason it says תאנה,
te'ena, רש"י says is it means it didn't just say you took
three apples off the tree, that would almost be like, you know,
obviously not distinct things. But what it means is they ripen in
different times. So it could be that even in one day, one
was ripe in the morning and one in the... One in the
afternoon and one in the evening, and that's three separate eatings. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says why doesn't that work according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir for making this real comparison to the ox? So
the גמרא Gemara says ליהוי חזקה דומיא דשור המועד. lehei chazakah dumya
deshor hamu'ad. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מה שור המועד בעידנא
דאיתא להאי נגיחה ליתא להאי נגיחה. ma shor hamu'ad be'idna de'ita lehai
negicha leita lehai negicha. When one goring is taking place, you don't
have the existence of the other goring. הכא נמי בעידנא דאיתא להאי
פירא איתא להאי פירא. hacha nami be'idna de'ita lehai peira eita lehai
peira. Here the other tree fruit can't exist yet. So even though
the other, you know, תאנה te'ena is not yet ripe, it still
is present, so it's not distinct enough from the first eating. So
the גמרא Gemara says fine. אכלה תלתא פירי, achala tlata peirei, that's
the different question about the גירסא, girsa, but anyway our גירסא girsa
is בתלתא יומי. betlata yomei. Let's say you had three fruit on
three separate days where the where they really it really had not
really, you know, it was really barely existed you know on the
on prior, כגון צלף, kegon tzelaf, like צלף. tzelaf. I what צלף
tzelaf is? Caper-bush. Okay. So apparently caper-bush, you know, the berries are
not like are very tiny. So they real it's almost like when
you ate one berry, one ripened berry one day, the other berries
weren't really in existence. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say they
were, they were tiny, they just weren't in existence they weren't big
yet. But anyway the גמרא Gemara says ליהוי חזקה, lehei chazakah, let
that be a חזקה. So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם פירא
מיהא איתא ומימהו דקמימהו ואזלו. hatam peira miha eita umimhu dekaminhu ve'azlu.
No, no, no, that still doesn't work. They're still not distinct enough
because the fruits existed. They weren't finished, but they still existed all
on the same day. Fine, says the גמרא. Gemara. אכלה תלתא פירי
בתלתין יומין. achala tlata peirei betlatzin yomin. Let's say it was three
different fruit on you know over 30 days. כגון אספסתא, kegon aspasta,
like אספסתא, aspasta, which is like a fodder. So apparently you can
cut it down and and you know and eat it and then
it'll grow back. So the גמרא Gemara you know and so you
can do that over 30 days you can get three you know
cutting downs of this of the young shoots or whatever it is
and that really is something you fully cut down and then it
grew back. ליהוי חזקה, lehei chazakah, let that work. So the גמרא
Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what would be the case? דקדיד ואכיל דקדיד ואכיל, dekadid ve'achil dekadid
ve'achil, you cut it down like you've quickly cut it and then
you quickly cut it, you know, you cut it down before it
had fully grown. So the גמרא Gemara says nah, that doesn't count.
התם משמוטי דקמשמיט ואכיל. hatam mishmotei dekamishmit ve'achil.
There you're just basically, you know, like sneaking away and eating. So
the way רש"י says is that you're not like you
mean like some part is always there, right?
No, but it
had not no, but it had not fully grown. So you're just
when you're just, you know, חאפינג khaping a quick, you're like you're
like not really eating a full fruit, you're just like quickly grabbing
something as soon as it grows. That's not a full eating. So
גמרא Gemara says fine. So the גמרא Gemara says אכלה תלתא פירי
בתלתא ירחי, achala tlata peirei betlata yarchi,
fine. Let's just fine. We'll go up to 30, we'll go up
to three months. כגון אספסתא, kegon aspasta, אספסתא, aspasta, it really does
grow fully each month. So fully grows in a month, you cut
it down, you eat it. It fully grows another month, you cut
it down, you eat it. So still, fine, the גמרא Gemara says
you should not need three years. If according to רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir logic that three times in a short period of time should
work, I can get you three full eatings of three separate you
know growths in three months. Let that work. The גמרא Gemara says,
you know what? Maybe it does. מאן הני אושאי רבי ישמעאל. man
hanei oushayei Rabbi Yishmael. Yeah. Who are these that come from אושא
Usha that have this tradition from אושא? Usha? It's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Ishmael. דרבי ישמעאל הכי נמי. de'Rabbi Yishmael hachi nami. Yeah, it would
work according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. דתנן at the end of
our משנה, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael אומר: במה דברים אמורים בשדה לבן.
be'me devarim amurim besdei lavan. When is it that you need three
years? When you're dealing with a wheat field, that it doesn't grow
back right away. אבל בשדה אילן, aval besdei ilan, if you have
some type of stuff that grows quickly or you know that can
produce three different types of harvests in a short period of
time, even though
the actual fruit that he's talking about doesn't grow in a month.
Right.
But the point still is but let's just finish
כנס את תבואתו ומסק את זיתיו וכנס את קיצו הרי אלו שלש
שנים, kanas et tevu'ato umasak et zeito vechanas et kitzo harei elu
shalosh shanim,
it works. So the point being though, and this is the basic
point of the גמרא, Gemara, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael? really is saying
you don't need three years. It's not about length of time. It's
about units. You need three harvests. So אין הכי נמי, ein hachi
nami, that actually fits very well with the שור המועד shor hamu'ad
comparison. You need three acts of goring, you need three acts of
I mean that can't be trivial, but it has to be three
acts of harvesting in some type of produce. And that constitutes even
though it's not giving the guy a lot of an opportunity to
respond, that is three separate acts that demonstrate distinct from one another,
that demonstrate that you're the owner. Okay, so at this stage the
גמרא Gemara has not mentioned one word of lack of provocation is
evidence that you must be the owner. It's all very formalistic. Three
things, okay, in a context where, okay, where it's being framed by
your making a claim, but and that basically establishes you
presumably. you didn't legitimately buy it, but that act, the demonstration, the
possession with that claim and the owner's silence that gives meaning to
that claim, that itself makes you the owner. That's the שור המועד
Shor Hamuad model. So now the גמרא Gemara says ורבנן מאי? v'rabbanan
mai? Now how about the rabbis who argue on רבי ישמעאל? They
obviously must have a different model for the idea of חזקה. It's
already 8:30, so we will end here and we will see the
what we sort of assume is the more rational model for שור
החזקה, Shor HaChazaka, the less formalistic one, we will begin with that
tomorrow.